Dendritic pattern, a concept that took
the Nyx community by storm earlier last
year, promising to simplify the
structure of your Nyx projects, improve
readability and scalability. But how
does it actually work and is it really
worth it? Today we will find an answer
to these questions. So without further
ado, let's get right into it. So, the
pattern traces back to a Nixos discourse
thread from last year where Mighty IM
shared his findings showing how turning
every Nyx file into a flake parts module
made his projects much easier to work
with. What this meant is essentially
instead of having a flake.nix file,
importing various modules, packages, and
shells, having to juggle all those files
with their own unique structures. The
approach was to wrap each file with a
flake parts module, making them all
follow a consistent and predictable
structure. Instead of just being a
package, the package file would now be
exporting a package under a certain name
to our flakes outputs. And instead of
being Nexos modules, our module files
would now be exporting Nexos modules,
making the Molly part of one greater
module system with each file being top
level and self-sufficient, which in turn
also allows us to forget about any
relative imports and just import every
file automatically because they can all
just reference each other by output name
anyway, eliminating any glue code. And
moreover, with our Nyx faster and flake
parts modules, we can actually have
several outputs per module, allowing us
to clump related stuff together, making
your config even more readable. You
could have a flake parts module
outputting a Nexus system with its main
configuration module, a related home
manager module, and some sort of system
specific package with all of them not
only being accessible to one another,
but also to every other part of your
flakes outputs. That was the general
idea. But to implement this yourself,
you will of course need to know how to
use flake parts. So before we proceed to
the actual code part, I highly recommend
you to check out the flake parts video
from the channel because it will all
make a lot more sense after you watch
it. So now let's start with an empty
flake. The most basic flake parts flake
to be specific. This is how it looks
normally. But to make our life easier
and get rid of manual imports, let's
also grab the import tree flake and use
it to import the new modules directory
recursively. And that's basically all
there is to it. So now we can proceed to
make some flake parts modules. For
example, let's start with a basic Nixx
module and create a Nyx file called my
first module.nix. We can put some
options inside and assume that we will
later reuse it for various Nexos hosts.
Now let's create a Nixos system module
that will output a Nixos system along
with its main configuration module. The
system can now access both its main
module and the module we created earlier
by taking them from flake self which is
basically your flakes's outputs. We
could also go ahead and create yet
another file exporting some kind of
package and then use that package in one
of our Nexus modules by once again just
taking it from self. Notice how we
didn't have to import anything manually
and how the purpose of each of our files
is abundantly clear with no extra
context. you open any of the files and
immediately understand what it does.
Plus, since all of your packages and
modules are stored in the outputs, you
obviously get the benefits of being able
to access them all externally, allowing
you to run the packages from your flake
with Nyx run or share your modules with
your friends. To go a step further, we
can also restructure our modules
directory. Put the Nexos modules in the
Nexos module subdirectory, our system in
the host directory, make another one for
packages and shells, and just continue
to build your flake, moving files around
whenever you please with no
consequences. Just make sure to do some
research on flake parts because with
your files turning flake parts modules,
you will have to use flake parts options
correctly like not nesting modules,
flake parts will not understand how to
merge them if you do it like this and
importing correct flake parts modules to
get options for external projects like
home manager. So to answer the question
from the beginning, is the dendritic
pattern really worth it? I personally
think it absolutely does and I have
already switched my Nexus configuration
to it many months ago. There is of
course more to it because when you dig
deeper there is a ton of ways to
implement it differently and projects
that aim to extend it. But I guess
that's a topic for another video, but
let me know what you think. Are you
using the dendritic pattern already or
perhaps considering to give it a try?
Let me know in the comment section. And
now I'd like to thank all the amazing
people that support the channel and keep
it going for all the generous monthly
and recent donations. They really mean
the world to me. And as always, don't
forget to check out our Discord server.
Leave a like or a comment if you enjoyed
this video, or subscribe if you are
feeling extra generous. Thanks for
watching, and I'll see you in the next
one.